Guide to the Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture Records, 1979-2017 and undated UA.09.16.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture records
1979-2017 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
UA.09.16.0001
7.5 Linear Feet 4500 items
The Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture was established in 1983 to share information about Africana and African-American culture with both the Duke and Durham communities. The collection contains materials regarding the general origins, development, and oversight of the Mary Lou Williams Center, as well as files related to programming hosted by, or sponsored by the Center. There are also a small number of files, mostly course materials, related to Leon Latimer Dunkley, Jr., who was the director of the Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture from 1999-2005.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
Provenance
The Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1997-1998, and 2018.
Historical Note
The Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture (MLWC) was established in 1983 to share information about Africana and African-American culture with both the Duke and Durham communities. It is named for the jazz pianist and composer Mary Lou Williams who was a Duke Artist-in-Residence from 1977 until her death in 1981. The Mary Lou Williams Center (as described on its website) seeks to:
"... promote racial understanding, build community, and foster an appreciation for and increase knowledge of Black people, Black history, Black culture, and the vast contributions of people of the African Diaspora. We provide programs and services which contribute to the successful academic and personal development of Black students at Duke University and positively impact the lives of all those whom they encounter. We seek to be a hub for information and activity related to Black students, alumni, and other Black members of the Duke community. We welcome all who seek to engage with and be empowered by a greater understanding of Black experience."
Collection Overview
The Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture records contain materials regarding the general origins, development, and oversight of the Mary Lou Williams Center, as well as files related to programming hosted by, or sponsored by the Center, or at other black culture centers and in higher education in general. Among the materials are articles; plans; Board of Directors meeting minutes, agendas, and draft policies; event and exhibit flyers; black-and-white photographs; mailing and contact lists; correspondence, reports, and budgets; and reservations. Many of the events involve poetry or jazz. There are also a small number of files, mostly course planning materials, related to Leon Latimer Dunkley, Jr., was the director of the Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture from 1999-2005.
Related Material
Black Student Alliance records, 1969-2006.
University Archives, Duke University.
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948 - 2001 and undated.
University Archives, Duke University.
University Archives Photograph Collection, 1861-ongoing.
University Archives, Duke University.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Administrative, Programming/Events, and Leon Dunkley papers.
Conditions Governing Access
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees. Contact Research Services for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials have not been screened for sensitive or restricted content. Staff will need to screen materials before use. Please contact Research Services for more information.
African American college students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Black-and-white photographs; African Americans -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- Education (Higher); Jazz -- North Carolina -- Durham; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century; Special events -- Planning; Dunkley, Leon Latimer
- Administrative
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative Files Series contains materials regarding the general origins, development, and oversight of the Mary Lou Williams Center, along with materials documenting its staffing. There are also subject files related to programming, especially at other black culture centers and in higher education in general. Among the materials are articles; plans; Board of Directors meeting minutes, agendas, and draft policies; event and exhibit flyers; black-and-white photographs; mailing and contact lists; correspondence, reports, and budgets; and reservations.
  Conditions Governing Access
  For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
  Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees. Contact Research Services for more information.
  Materials have not been screened for sensitive or restricted content. Staff will need to screen materials before use. Please contact Research Services for more information.
  - General
    Arrangement
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Articles, 1979-1994 (Box 1)
    - Planning and Organizing Info., 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Event and exhibit flyers, 1981-1998 (Box 1)
    - Reservations for the Mary Lou Williams Black Cultural Center, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors, Minutes and Agendas, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Invitations and Programs for MLWC Opening Ceremonies, 1983-2004 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Edward Hill, 1984-1995; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Photos, 1988 and undated (Box 1)
    - Minority List, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Humanities Council Mary Lou Williams Center Proposal, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Mailing List, 1991-1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2022.
    - Stationary and Business Cards, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Maureen Meetings, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence & Reports, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2026.
    - Assorted Correspondence, Notes, Reservation Requests, 1996-2002; 3 folders (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2027.
    - Campus Community Development, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Contacts, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2023.
    - Mailing List, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Job Descriptions, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2025.
    - Documents--BOT, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      Board of Trustees restriction until 2050.
    - Website, 1998-2004 (Box 1)
    - Development, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Panhellenic, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Media, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
    - Contacts, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Mailing List, 2000 (Box 1)
    - LatinX Events, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2028.
    - Reservations, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - Floor Plans, 2002 (Box 1)
    - President's Council on Black Affairs, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Budget Proposals and Expenses, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - Mailing List, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Recruitment, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Sister Mentors articles, 2003-2007 (Box 1)
    - Career Center Week, 2004 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2029.
    - Public Identity, 2005 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2030.
    - Comm. ASAP Lists, 2006-2008 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2033.
    - Staff Manual, 2007 (Box 1)
      Administrative restriction until 2032.
    - Brochures and Resource Guides, 2008-2017 (Box 1)
    - Contacts, undated (Box 1)
  - Subject Files
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - ABCC 9th Annual Conference, 1999 (Box 2)
      Administrative restriction until 2024.
    - American Red Cross, undated (Box 2)
    - Art exhibits, 1986-2001 (Box 2)
    - Association for Black Culture Centers, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Assorted advertisements, 1997-2001 (Box 2)
    - Assorted pamphlets, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Black Business Expo, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Black Issues in Higher Education, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Bulletins, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - CDS, Healing Pages, Newspapers, 1999-2004 (Box 2)
    - Center for Creative Leadership, undated (Box 2)
    - Charter school, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Black Performing Arts - Stanford, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Cultural events, 1985-2003 (Box 2)
    - Event brochures, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Film festivals and other programs, 1998-2004 (Box 2)
    - Followers: A film by Jonathan M. Flicker, 1999 (Box 2)
    - For Colored Boys Who Have Considered Homicide (film), 1999 (Box 2)
    - Gaines, 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - General, 1984-1994 (Box 2)
    - Heritage Center, undated (Box 2)
    - Honor council, undated (Box 2)
    - The Jazz Messengers: The Legacy of Art Blakey, 1988 March (Box 2)
    - John Hope Franklin Center, 2000 (Box 2)
      Administrative restriction until 2025
    - Leadership, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
    - Legacy, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Living the Dream, 1994-1996 (Box 2)
      Administrative restriction until 2021.
    - Malcolm X and the 21st century Black consciousness, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Martin Luther King, undated (Box 2)
    - Miss Ella J. Baker and the Birth of SNCC (event), 2000 (Box 2)
    - Moss, Dean, 1999 (Box 2)
    - NASPA, 1997 (Box 2)
    - National Black Theatre Festival, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets, Brochures, Press Kits, 1992-2003 (Box 2)
    - Performers--National, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Programming at other schools, 1996-2009 (Box 2)
      Administrative restriction until 2034.
    - Progressive Movement, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Rape Crisis of Durham, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Robeson, Paul, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - UNC Black Cultural Center, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
- Programming/Events
  The Programming/Events Series chronicles activities hosted by, or sponsored by the Center, including its jazz festival, poetry readings by individuals, as well as plans and proposals for film, exhibit, and poetry series and other programs. Includes planning documents, flyers and programs, resumes of artists and presenters, expense reports, and published articles and advertising.
  - Jazz on the Green
    - Jazz on the Green, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1985 April 12-14 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1993 September 11 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Complimentary Ticket List for Page, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green Jacky McClain, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1998; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Jazz, 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, 2001-2002; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Jazz on the Green, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry
    - Adisa, Opol, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Allen, Geri, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Ammons, Shiriette, undated (Box 3)
    - Baker, Houston, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Bandela, Asha, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Baraka, Amiri, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Barriteau, Violet Eudine, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Beisel, NIcole, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Benson, Tish, 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Bethel, Marion, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Caesar, Shirley, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Campbell, Lawrence, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Chandler, Nahum, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Chiduya, Farai, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Childs, Carol, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Chung, David, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Clark, Keith, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Clifton, Lucille, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Cohen, Cathy, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Coleman, Wanda, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Cooper, Carolyn, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Dahl, Linda, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Darker Face of the Earth, undated (Box 3)
    - Davis, Ursula, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Diggs, Natasha Latasha, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Dunkley, Juanita Carol, 1998-2001 (Box 4)
    - Dunye, Cheryl, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Fannell, Yvette, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Faraji, Salim, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Finch, Charles, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Finny, Nikki, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Forman, Ruth, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Frederick, Rhonda, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Frye, Gladys, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Gayles, Gloria Wade, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Gidding, Paula, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Glenn, R.C., 2000 (Box 4)
    - Gonzales, Michelle, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Goodman, Amy (Mumia Abu-Jamal), 1999 (Box 4)
    - Grant, Craig (Mums), 1999 (Box 4)
    - Gray, Andre Leon, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Green, Richard, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Hasan, Jefferies, undated (Box 4)
    - Harris, Michael, 1997-1999 (Box 4)
    - Haynes, Camika, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Hengino, Titas, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Hine, Darlene Clark, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Humphrey, Margo, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Hunter, Tera, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Jefferies, Hasan, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Jobsen, Mara, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Tony, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Johnson-Coleman, Lorraine, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Jones, Eric, undated (Box 4)
    - Joseph, Ambassador James, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Keaton, Martin, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Ladd, Michael (Poet), 1998-2000 (Box 4)
    - Lee, Spike, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - Lincoln, C. Eric, 1998-2000 (Box 4)
    - Luyala, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Manou, Lelawatte, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Marika, Dave, undated (Box 4)
    - Martin, Wado, undated (Box 4)
    - Mason, Keith, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Mateinger, Ryan, 2001 (Box 4)
    - McHenry, Elizabeth, 1999 (Box 4)
    - McKea, Ama Dawn, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Miller, E. Ethelbert, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Moore, Jessica C., 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Morris, Tracie, 1998 (Box 4)
    - MOVE, undated (Box 4)
    - Muller, Carol Ann, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Nashold, Jim, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Naylor, Gloria, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Newsome, Thomas, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Norris, Henri, 2000 (Box 4)
    - O'Brien, Father Peter, undated (Box 4)
    - Oubre, Hayward, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Payne, Charles, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Peck, Sabrina, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Pendergraft, Norman and Bullock, Mable, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Perdoma, Willie, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Portle, Raymond, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Peterson, Liza Jessie, undated (Box 4)
    - Rauling, Hunter (inaugural speech), 1999 (Box 4)
    - Ross, Lawrence, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Rucker, Ursula, undated (Box 4)
    - Rux, Carl Hancock, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Sapphire (Lofton, Ramona), 2002 (Box 4)
    - Schubert, Monique Art Exhibit, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Sigma Gamma Rho Sorority Inc., undated (Box 4)
    - Shange, Ntozake, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Simmons, Bradley, 1997-1999 (Box 4)
    - Simmons, Shariff, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Smith, Anna Deavere, 1995-1997 (Box 4)
    - Sneed, Laurel C., 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Soto, Gary, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Stewart, Dianne, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Sulaiman, Amir (BSAI), 2001 (Box 4)
    - Takaki, Ron, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Taylor, Timothy, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Thompson, Becky, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Tirro, Frank, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Troupe, Quincy, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Weiss, Alex, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Wells, Mark, undated (Box 4)
    - White, Barnetta, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Whitehead, Colson, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Willis, Deborah, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Woodard, Komozi, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Planning and meetings
    Arranged chronologically
    Materials have not been screened for sensitive or restricted content. Staff will need to screen materials before use. Please contact Research Services for more information
    - Programming ideas, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Event calendars, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Timothy Taylor, 1998-2001 (Box 4)
    - Art show, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Art show placards, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Programming meetings, 1999-2001 (Box 4)
    - Duke Institute of the Arts, 1999-2004 (Box 4)
    - Break for a Change, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Stephen Jaffe Jazz Art Initiative, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - Proposals, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
    - Julian Abele Awards, Honor Ceremony, Black Books, Assorted flyers, 2000-2012 (Box 4)
    - Afro-Cuban Ensemble, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Calendar, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Race, Sex, and God, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Dr. Dunkley, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Phoenix poetry series, 2003 (Box 4)
    - 20/40, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Art exhibition, 2003 (Box 4)
    - 4.9 FCJL, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - August meeting notes, 2005 (Box 4)
    - MLW Diasporic Film Festival, 2006 (Box 4)
      Administrative restriction until 2031.
    - 25th anniversary, 2007-2008 (Box 4)
    - Programming binder, 2008-2009; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Event flyers, 2008-2012 (Box 5)
    - In the making, 2012-2013 (Box 5)
      Administrative restriction until 2038.
    - Accomodations, undated (Box 5)
  - Events
    Arranged alphabetically
    - 5 Women, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Art Gallery, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Artist-in-residence, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Black Male Exhibition, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Blue Roach, 1994-2001 (Box 5)
    - C.T.'s Conferences; Anderson, Delores, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Completed 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Co-sponsorship and publicity: Blue Roach administration, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Cultural Extravaganza, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Death Penalty, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Event flyers, 1984-1994 (Box 5)
    - Event flyers, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Hollis Chatelain textile art, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Images of our Heritage, 2007 (Box 5)
    - Miles and Miles, 1994 (Box 5)
    - MLW Programming Completed 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - MLW Programming Committee 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Music on my Mind, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Performances 1998-2001 (Box 5)
    - Phillips 1998-1999 programs (Box 5)
    - Poets 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Posters, 2011 (Box 5)
    - Program flyers, 1991-2000 (Box 5)
    - Souls in Touch exhibit, 2002 (Box 5)
    - South Africa, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Speakers for 1999-2000 (Box 5)
- Leon Dunkley papers
  Leon Latimer Dunkley, Jr., was the director of the Mary Lou Williams Center for Black Culture from 1999-2005. The Leon Dunkley Papers Series documents courses Dunkley offered from 1999-2002, and also contains an undated planning notebook, and other personal and planning notes and poetry.
  - Course materials: Race and music in the 20th century, 2000 (Box 5)
  - House course Spring 99-00, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - House course 2002-Fall (Box 5)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Permission number for class 99-00, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Untitled notes and poetry, 1999 (Box 5)